course of IIT Kharagpur and I teach in the computer science engineering department. I
will be taking this course on computer networks. So, we will be having about 40 lectures in
the series. So, today we will start with an introductory lecture which is about the
emergence of computer networks at brief history and a little bit about the protocols and
reference models which is an abstract view of computer networks.
The textbooks for the course will be these three computer networking, a top down approach
featuring internet that is one by Kurov, data and computer communication by William
Stolling and computer networks by A.S. Stanenbaum. So, some of the material that we will be covering
here verbally as well as in the slide will be from these books.
Now the first question is what is a computer network? So, a computer network is a number
of computers also known as nodes connected by some communication lines. So, we have these
computers which are connected by some communication lines. So, two computers connected to the
network can communicate with each other through other nodes if they are not directly connected
which means that computer does not have to be connected to all the other computers in
the network in order to communicate with any of them. It may be an indirect communication
via some other computer and the other point is that these nodes they are computers, but
some of them are not computers, some of them are sort of network devices. Now there are
various kinds of network devices like switches, routers, etcetera. So, they could also, so
they facilitate the communication and running of this entire network. So, they are also
taken as nodes in the network. So, finally we have some of the nodes, some nodes which
may be either computers or there may be network devices like switches and routers and there
is a communication between them. This communication of course can be of various types we will
come to that presently. So, the computers can communicate with each other. Now what do they
communicate? They exchange information between different computers. Now this information could
be of any kind of information. They could be data used by a program or they could be
some program itself or it could be any kind of information really. So, that is one
of the basic and major use of computer network. Of course, there are other specialized uses
of computer network. For example, interconnected small computers can replace a large computer.
For example, you have a very large computation to perform and so further either you need
a very powerful and very large computer which may be costly. The other option could
be that you break up this work into very small pieces and assign them to the small computer.
So, the small computers sort of do the computation on that small chunk of the problem and then
they communicate with each other to form the final solution. Then the other uses computer
network which is coming into Vogue very much these days is that you can use this network
as a communication tool. We know the very basic say for example, you send emails to I mean
you can send emails to almost anybody these days and that is really a very cheap and
very fast mode of communication. Secondly, the computer network could also be used
for direct communication like say you could have communicate through voice over a computer
network, you can communicate through video over a computer network. So, all these different
communication is converging into this computer network and as a matter of fact nowadays when
we talk about the network we do not look upon it just as a computer network as a
matter of fact it is the bedrock on which say all this computing communication all
these are converging and then of course, you have some application which are necessarily
of distributed nature. For example, let us say railway reservation system now obviously
even if you had a large computer to handle all the railway reservations in the world
in one place, but you would not want all the people to go to one place and sort
of form a huge queue. So, you want to distribute this functionality that means, for that of booking
ticket all over the country and that is what we do. So, these are sort of examples of
distributed system. So, this is a distributed reservation system. Similarly, there could
be other kinds of distributed system, there could be distributed databases and all
kinds of applications. So, that is the other application of networks.
Now, a quick look at the history of this computers first and then we will sort of focus on computer
network. Well, in 1948 we have the first commercial computer installed it was an
Univac that was a big company once upon a time and then in 1958 the first US communication
satellite became operational. So, you see the network always has these two components
one is that you have to have this computer and then you have to have this communication
channel and satellite communication is of course, one of an important medium of communication
then in 1964 we have an airline reservation system which uses some kind of a packet switching
network it was proposed by the RAND Corporation and in 1969 ARPANET the first packet switching
network began its operation. This was actually a watershed event as we will see this had
very far reaching impact on the way computer networks developed.
Then in 1971 we have the first computer chip previous computers were made through very low
level gates and all, but the first 4 bit small computer chip with 2300 transistors and they
became available in 1971. In 1972 Ethernet specifications were formulated. Now, this
Ethernet is one protocol so to say. So, we will talk about protocols and different kinds
of protocols and Ethernet remains one of the most important network protocols that we
use. So, that was first formulated in 1972. In 1974 IBM introduced its own version of
network in SNA. Then in 1975 Altair 8800 first commercial microcomputer that was sold as a
kit. So, we are actually looking at the very brief history of computers in general. So, in
1975 we had the Paul Allen and Bill Gates getting together which eventually formed the
Microsoft. We all know about Microsoft. 1976 Woznik and Job built Apple one. So, Apple also
had a lot of contribution to make in computers in various aspects and the window system that
we see today almost everywhere. It was basically it started from Apple computers.
In 1979 we had the VC calc as the first commercial spreadsheet. So, that is a very popular application
of computer these days. In 1981 IBM introduced IBM PC on with one floppy drive. Later on they
changed it with a drive and a hard drive also. And in 1983 TCP IP. So, this TCP IP
is another network protocol that we are using. Actually we use both Ethernet and TCP IP. So,
we actually we have different protocols which are running on the network we require and
how these different protocols are arranged and how they are used that I will cover today
in the second part of the lecture. So, this TCP IP is another important protocol
that is still very much different today that became the official protocol of ARPANET.
Remember ARPANET we talked about that is a network which was set up in USA under DRDO and
which had a very far reaching impact on the way network developed. In 1984 Apple introduced
GUI with Apple Macintosh and 1986 we see the first laptop PCs 88. So, IBM gives a multitasking
OS for the PCs. 1989 Microsoft releases Windows which is another multitasking system in that
is the Microsoft version. 1989 NSF that is the National Sound Foundation of USA. It replaces
ARPANET as internet backbone and then WWW was invented by CERN physicist Tim Berners-Lee
in 1991. So, this advent of WWW that means the worldwide web really made the network very
very popular. So, there was this kind of positive feedback going on as it became more popular
more and more people jumped into it as people showed their interest. So, commercial companies
also then became interested because there would be a market for something in networks
that they do and when the commercial companies developed something naturally it became more
easier to use the network they had more functionalities. So, more people became interested. So, that
was the positive loop which made this I mean actually then the growth of network
in the past decade that means in the 90s let us say has been absolutely phenomenal
and if the basic so called killer app that is the killer application the application which
attracted so many people to network was this WWW which was invented in 1991. In 1992 Mosaic
released first GUI web browser. So, that was a web browser the Netscape became the
popular web browser. Microsoft of course had its own version of Microsoft Explorer.
So, that was another browser and then it all built up into some kind of a frenzy and in
2000 we had this dot com so called dot com meltdown that means I mean people became
absolutely frenzied about the growth of computer and of course such a frenzy cannot
go on forever. So, it has to come to a halt. So, it did in 2000, but the development
of networks and its utility and important remains. So, now let us go to a brief history
more focused on the network itself. So, that part so we were in general talking about the
computing scene in general. So, in mid 1960s USA department of defense
wanted a command and control network that could survive a nuclear attack. Now, if
something had to survive a nuclear attack then you have to distribute it. So, that
was one strong reason that we wanted distributed system and if you have a distributed
system this system must be able to communicate. So, that was the seed of this project. The
subnet should consist of some Honeywell 12kw intermediate message processors. So, there
are some kind of early network devices you might say which are connected by 64 kbps
line. These IMPs or intermediate message processors were connected to the various computers and
IMPs themselves were connected by telephone lines from telephone companies. Later the
IMP software was changed to terminal interface processors which allowed the connection
of terminals. In 1970s NSF set up a machine connected to the ARPANET to which other
universities could develop and connect. Now, this became very important in the sense that
many people were interested in this. So, NSF upgraded their system in various ways and
by mid 1980s NSF built a new backbone to connect with supercomputing centers to some
regional network. So, this backbone was upgraded to 448 kbps and then to 1.5 mbps
and once this fiber backbone was there communication was really fast. So, it allowed network
connection to hundreds of thousands of universities, research labs, libraries, museums etcetera.
So, as the growth continued now commercial houses began to take notice and to join
the decentralized model began to take hold. And as I mean as I just described earlier
that as the commercial people joined. So, there was a lot of innovation by a lot of
people. One of the major driving force in the computing network in the past decades
or even now may be has been the role of so called startup companies. By startup
companies that means that some young engineers may be or some young people they had
some very bright idea which they developed to a certain extent. And if when that was sort
of proven then some big company would possibly buy up their company or give them money to
get access to this kind of technology. And a lot of people and there were so many
success stories that a lot of people got interested in it and when a lot of people
think about a problem naturally there is a lot of innovation. So, that is how computer
networks had an explosive growth in the whole of 90s and even in the this century there
is a 21st century I mean the growth is going on. Although the frenzy in the stock
exchanges etcetera about this dot com company that sort of crashed in 2000, but the
growth in the field of networks and it used in various walks of life that is
continuing. With this brief historical background now let us come to the networks
and some kind of a structure or some kind of an abstract view of this computer network.
We have I have already mentioned that computer network would be a number of nodes
and nodes could be computer or nodes could be network devices also which are
connected by some communication lines. Now, when I say that of course sometimes things
are not so simple sometimes you do have a line between two nodes let us say. So, giving us
the so called point to point communication that means one node A is communicating directly
to one another node B where A and B are connected by a direct line let us say it
could be a physically some copper line or some fiber line etcetera.
So, but this point to point connection could be so in the simplest case they are actually
dedicated, but in the dedicated case also we have some different cases for example you
could have a simplex communication by simplex communication we mean that communication can
go in only one direction in that line. It could be half duplex by half duplex that means
that is the communication could go both ways either way either from A to B or from B to
A, but only in one direction at a time and full duplex of course that A and B can communicate
with each other simultaneously there is parallely at the same time. So, that means
there is communication from A to B and from B to A at the same time. So, these are the
different kinds of dedicated line then if the nodes are not say computer some network
devices specifically if they are sort of multiplexer then we could share a point to
point medium that means there is one line from A to B, but A is connected to a lot of other
nodes let us say A 1, A 2 to A n and B is connected again to a lot of other nodes say
B 1, B 2 to B n and they could all these A i's and B i's they could all communicate
through this one single line which is between A and B. So, this we will see later how
such a thing can be done. So, this business of sharing a link over time or whatever even
parallely sometimes that is possible. So, sharing this link by multiple people that is called
multiplexing. So, these are the different kinds of point to point links, but point
to point links are not the only things we have. For example, we could have a broadcast
kind of link. For example, if you have a satellite communication, a satellite sort of
throws its signal all over the country or may be all over the region. So, that is something
which is being broadcast everything. So, you cannot really put it down as a point
to point link between something, but of course you could use that shared medium
and a broadcast in some way to make temporary point to point links or your application may
be such that you want to broadcast something. For example, we broadcast TV signal similarly
there are things you might want to broadcast all over. So, there could be. So, this broadcast
medium again could be dedicated to some user or it could be shared that means it is
shared between multiple user. So, there the term that is used is multiple access a medium
to which different users are connected at different point and it is a broadcast kind of medium.
So, in a distributed fashion they have some protocol of deciding how to share this because
if it is in the same place you can the business of sharing become somewhat easier.
So, you can multiply it, but if it is if the nodes themselves are distributed over this broadcast
medium physically distributed that is. So, you will have to have some kind of protocol
so that is called multiple access. So, you can have a shared broadcast medium also that
is also quite common. And then finally we have this something
which is in between broadcasting and point to point which is called multicasting. This
means that say we have a group I have say some friends and I want to send some things
which not to one particular friend, but to my group of friends, but to know others.
So, multicasting is basically giving a I mean communicating to a specified group.
So, using such communication link we have this computer network and the network themselves
are I mean quite often popularly they are sort of divided into local area network, metropolitan
area network and wide area network. Local area network is just that which means that
it is local that means it is sort of it is sort of limited to may be one building or may
be to a small group of building. So, it is its size is small that is one thing.
There are some other things about local area network which makes the issues of local
area network somewhat different from a larger network. So, and that is that the local
area network would usually be privately owned. Now, how does ownership come into picture?
Ownership comes into picture because if you have a same owner for the entire network then
you can have the same policy. So, which is not the case if it is a very
wide area network, we will come to that wide area network that is the other case
where there may be I mean the different parts of I mean there are various nodes
which are connected to this wide area network. The nodes may belong to very different
people and they may have very different ideas about what should be done and about
all their policies. So, that makes that wide area networking somewhat different
from local area networking and in between we have this metropolitan area
network. Metropolitan area means say a network which is spread over a community
or maybe even a city. So, there are bigger sizes than local area network and there
one of the issues which is very important is the access issues which means that how
do you connect for example, you want to make an entire community network. So, how
do you connect each one of them because they are geographically more distributed
than a local area network. Local area network maybe you would like to sometimes
you would use welders sometimes you would just simply draw weld and the cost will not
be very prohibitive, but in local area how we connect the people that becomes an
issue. So, that is the access issue and we have talked about the wide area network.
Wide area networks are costly that means naturally when you are talking
about communicating over maybe hundreds or thousands of kilometers. The communication
is costly the cost has come down and that is another thing which is historically
happened as more and more people got interested in the network technology
developed that is one side of the issue the other side of the issue is that the
volumes went up which means that the number of people who used the
network. So, the as the volumes went up the cost went down. So, the technology
improved on in one direction. So, that was one input into bringing down the cost
and the other issue was that more and more people started using it. So, the volume
to a particular company let us say developing something in the network area.
So, that went up. So, they could make it make things cheaper and as the
whole thing becomes cheaper and cheaper more and more people wanted to get
to join the network. But wide area network cost is still an issue and of course,
wide area network as I said that it is a it may connect various local area
networks. So, it is a network of networks or internet
work in or I mean as we know it very popularly that is the internet.
Now, let us look at abstract idea about the abstract idea about the network in
general. So, in the formal framework we have what are known as protocols. Now,
why do we need protocols in network? We need protocols in network because
network by its very nature they may connect various different people and as I
said various different people may have very different ideas about how things are
to be done. Now, if people have very different ideas about how things are
to be done then, but they have to agree on some common basis otherwise they cannot
communicate and this common basis is the protocol. So, there are actually there are
number of protocols which are used in any network and we will be getting into that,
but so you and I may have very different ideas about how some particular
thing may be done. So, I may be doing this in a certain way you may be doing
the same thing may be in a completely different way, but if you want to
communicate we have to agree on some minimum protocol that is the protocol. So,
these protocols are the building blocks of this network architecture. So, each
protocol object has two different interfaces. One is the service interface
that defines operations on this protocol and peer to peer interface which
defines messages exchanged with peer which means that for example, any
protocol so a protocol is let us say between peer. So, if in this diagram so these
allies so there are so these two boxes allies they are the these two allies
they are the different I mean peers and they communicate with each other through
this peer interface that is the protocol. Now, this protocol is supposed to
achieve something is supposed to do something for this it requires something
may be from some other so called layer. So, actually we have a layered
architecture and I am coming to that in the next slide. So, how this protocol is
to be invoked etcetera for this we have a service interface and between the
peers we have a peer interface. So, this is a so we have all these different
layers. So, we have this n plus 1th layer and nth layer and n minus 1th layer in
general. So, actually these how they are to be layered about that also there are
some standards and we will just look at two of them at this. So, let us say for
example, this networking business is broken up into I mean whatever the
jobs you have to do for achieving for smooth functioning of computer
network we break them up into different functionalities and these
functionalities are in different layers. Now, this is all in one place that
means in one node similarly another node which is connected to the network
will have its own layers and this at the same level let us say n and n
here their peers. So, there will be a protocol between this n and n whereas
there will be a service interface between the n plus 1th layer and nth layer
similarly there may be a service interface between the nth layer and n minus
1th layer and so on. So, let us see what they are like. So, as I said most
networks are organized as series of layer the task of each layer is to
give some service to the upper layer. So, that is the task of each
layer and any layer maintains a virtual connection with the
corresponding layer in a peer. So, this virtual connection any layer which
maintains a virtual connection this virtual connection is used for
running the peer to peer protocol whereas this is the service
interface the task of each layer. So, each layer performs certain tasks
of this whole networking business all right. So, each layer performs some task.
So, this task is a service to the upper layer similarly for performing this
task it may break it up into some sub task and some sub task may be
delegated to a lower layer. So, this layer would have its own
service interface to the lower layer whereas the its own task which
are whatever I mean assuming that the sub task is done by the
lower layer its own task is performed at the peer to peer level
using the corresponding protocol. So, there is peer to peer protocol
running between any two corresponding and communicating layer the
interface between the layers in the same node is well defined.
Well, another point is that the for this peer to peer protocol
mostly they go through what is what I have just now called a
virtual connection that means. So, what is a virtual connection
virtual connection means that well physically physical connection we
understand let us say two computers are connected by a wire.
Now, as I mentioned earlier two computers may not I mean it is not
necessary that the two computers need to be directly connected in
order to communicate it may be an indirect connection also that
means it is going through from one computer to another to
another then it is hopping from node to node and then it reaches
finally its destination. So, there is no direct physical
communication although let us say when you are searching the
internet let us say which is a very common experience these days.
So, you have connected to some computer which may be in the
opposite part of the globe. So, to you it appears that you
are sort of directly connected to that computer. So, whenever
you are clicking something over here something happens which
something happens means of course something happens. So, that
you are clicking of the mouse somehow that gets communicated to that
remote server remote web server and it may be the page
changes or something. So, there is there seem to be a direct
communication, but this communication is only virtual the
physical communication is only at the lowest layer where
physically something may be communicated by connected by
piece of wire or it may be connected by fiber optic
links or it may be connected by may be satellite links
whatever it is. So, that is a that is the physical
connection. So, that is why this for running all these
protocols these peers need to communicate and this
communicate is through a virtual connection. Now, the
implementation of each layer in each node is transparent to
other nodes. Now, actually this is the main point of having
this layered architecture that the implementation of each
layer in each node is transparent to the to the
other to other nodes. As I said that I may want to do this
one particular sub task in some some particular way I
means let us say some company X and then some company Y
wants to do the same thing may be in a different way.
Now, you need not stop any of them. So, long as they agree
on the protocol so long as they agree on the service
service layers as what is the service interface between
the different layers because upper layer service may be
given by some product of some company whereas the
lower layer of the lower layer is may be developed by
some other company. Now, once again if they can
decide on the interface between these two layers it
is all right. Now, then they are very free to do
it in their own way the same thing applies to the
peers. For example, say two nodes say two
particular layers in two particular nodes may be
peer and let us say these nodes are computer themselves.
Now, one may be a may be an IBM machine another may be
a Sun machine or something and they may have they
will have different operating system they will
have different processors etcetera. But so far as
the peer to peer protocol is concerned they agree.
So, these are the messages I will send and then
if I am expecting this kind of answer and he
said these are the kinds of messages that I
will accept and this kind of answer will be
given etcetera etcetera. So, that is how a
protocol goes. So, so long as they agree on this
protocol these two companies are free to develop
their product in their own way and when you
allow that naturally people can innovate
people can put in different things. So, long
as you are conforming to the standard of the
protocol and the interfaces etcetera you
can develop your own thing in a in your
own way and that is very good for the
development of the program of the of this
entire network and the other point is that
this is one way of abstracting out all
these unnecessary details from the for
example, any of these networking I mean
say network operating system in a
computer or a networking device they may
be very very complex indeed and some of
the complexity is special to the
implementer one implementer has decided to
implement something in a some particular
way and that will have a whole lot of details
now we are not really interested in that
one we want to abstract out of that.
So, we concentrate on these protocols and
the interfaces and the functionalities.
So, that gives us a fairly general
picture about the entire networking I
mean how networking is done and then
if you are really if you go into business
of developing some of these modules
yourself then you have to go into some
more nuts and bolts about how this service
can be given. Now, the protocols between
peer layers can be changed if the peers
all agree naturally if you are changing
the protocol all the peers have to
agree otherwise the communication will
break down. However, it need not be
referred to other layer. So, that is
another good thing about layering
that means when I am changing
something in this layer I may so long
as I am not changing anything in the
interface between the upper layer and
this my layer or between myself and the
lower layer so long as I am not changing
anything in the interface internally
whatever change I make will not matter.
So, that is the good point of this
layering and the service definition
tells what the layer does and nothing
else. That means nothing else means
nothing about the specifics of
implementation which may vary from
one vendor to another vendor. The
interface tells the process above it
how to access it, it specifies what the
parameters are and what results can be
expected. So, we have two I mentioned
here three models so three layered
models the most famous is the OSI
reference model which we will look
into some of the details and then
TCPIT reference model which is most
widely used actually. So, OSI reference
model I mean some part of it is
somewhat theoretical because many
people do not really do that and
they do not consider that part to be
very important. But TCPIT reference
model is something which is almost
ubiquitous and for ATM so the ATM is
one networking technology which is
rather complete technology I mentioned
here this here just as an example
so that is another kind of reference
model. So, there are all kinds of
different reference models sometimes
these models so these models are
basically a description of the
different layers that are there
and then naturally if you talk about
the layers of what that layer is
supposed to do that is what you say
and then how it is to be
interface with the layer above and
the layer below. So, since this is
just a number of layers one on top
of the other they are also referred
to as stacks sometimes. So, we call
about the TCPIT stack and OSI stack
and so on ATM stack. So, other
protocol stacks exist and new ones
are possible however to the extent
to which a particular model is
universally accepted is the key
to its success as I said that a
lot of thought went into OSI
reference model but in practice
TCPIT became much more prevalent.
So, let us see the OSI reference
model this has seven layers and
these layers are application layer
the presentation layer the
session layer the network layer
the data link layer and the physical
layer which means that in order
that people can communicate
over this network in a very
seamless manner the all the
jobs that are involved that
have been broken down into seven
parts and they are the different
seven layers. So, application layer
is something and then presentation
session network data link and physical
layer. So, each layer has some kind
of functionality and all these
functionalities together gives you
the network overall functionality
in the network. So, just a little
bit more about peer level
communication messages sent from
one application to another
application on different host. So, it
travels down the layers on the
sending machine and each layer adds
a header to be used by its
corresponding peer level and the
bottom layer which is the physical
layer sends the message to the
TCP machine. So, this is the
general scheme the point is
that suppose we start something
at the very top let us say in the
case of OSI we call it the
application layer. So, something
has something some communication has
been initiated at the application
layer. Now, this application layer
mind you is really it has its peer
let us say in the destination machine.
So, in the destination machine also
some application layer program is
running for example let us say you
are doing a telnet kind of thing
that means you are sort of logging
on to another machine. So, you are
doing a telnet to another machine. So,
you will start your telnet program
which will be a telnet client program
and the destination machine
will have will now the who will
sort of respond to a telnet client
only a telnet server we can respond
to a telnet client this telnet
server is in the remote machine.
So, these are the two modules
both of which are in the application
layer. Now, how telnet is an example
of a protocol this is an
application layer protocol and
what this protocol does how the
telnet client will request how the
telnet server will respond etcetera
these are the internals of this
particular protocol namely the
telnet protocol. Now, so far as the
telnet client or any of these
application program is concerned
when it tries to communicate to
another application program in
another machine it just knows
about this protocol and how things
are to be done at that layer. But
how is it how is this communication
to go from this machine to another
machine for this if you put the
whole thing in the same program then
that becomes very complicated that
was the idea of layering that means
so given a sort of virtual connection.
So, he will sort of for
communicating to the target
machine he will have some
data to sort of same. So, that
will add up to may be other
kinds of data and then
hand it over to the
lower layer in the same node.
Now, the lower layer similarly
may be running a protocol with the
corresponding layer in the
remote machine. So, for that
protocol it needs to do some
communication. So, for that
communication whatever message is
to be sent here that get added
to the original data which
was sent by the application
layer. So, this way as
the message to be sent
moves down the stack from
the originating machine at
each layer each layer is running
its own protocol which is here. So, it
has some message to the sort of
add give to his pair. So, they
will keep on adding it to this. So,
this becomes fatter and fatter as it
goes down. Now, as it goes down
to the physical layer
there it can now communicate
to the remote machine and in
the remote machine this will now
again move up the stack and at
each layer that particular
the program or whatever that
module in that layer he will
take out the message which has been
sent by its peer in the
source. So, that is how
communication will go on for
all these protocols. So,
sending
a message. So,
received on the receiving side
and it is passed up through each
layer and each layer reads the
corresponding header. That
means the corresponding header which
has been sent by
the by its own peer
on the from the source
machine. So, this is an
example. Let us say
we have two machines
and one machine is a DOS
machine. That means it is
some DOS is of course
an old operating system which
used to run on PCs and
which was there from the
Microsoft DOS and the PC DOS
etc. IBM DOS was there and
Macintosh was a different company
as I mentioned. So, these two
can still communicate that means
they are two different machines.
But this original data
which was there which was
which sort of originated from the
application layer. Now, there is a
presentation layer. Now, this
presentation layer will add its
own presentation header to this
original data. Now, this whole
thing becomes sort of data
for the next layer namely the
session layer. So, session layer
will add its own header. So, as
I said that the original data
becomes fatter and fatter
and fatter till it comes to
the physical layer. Now, at the
physical layer data is
actually sent let us say in
one hop to the destination
machine. Now, here as
this whole fat packet
travels up each
layer will strip
off its corresponding header
which is coming from its peer
layer in the source. So, that is
how each of the peers
can communicate and each of
them has a virtual connection
with the destination
machine although the actual
connection is the physical
connection. So, these are
the seven protocol
layers. Now, we are going
bottom up and I will just tell
you in brief later on I will
just go down to how they are
sort of some more details
about each of these layer.
So, first is the physical link
which is how to
transmit the bits
and then we have
the data link layer that is
how to transmit frames. Now, what is
the difference between transmitting bits
and transmitting frames we will see
to that, but a data link
basically is a direct connection
that means how two computers
which are directly or two nodes which
are directly connected to each other
how they will communicate that is a
matter of data link layer.
Now, as mentioned earlier
computers need not be directly
connected to each other in order
to communicate they have to be
connected to the network somehow
or other. So, if there is
there are say two machines A and
B or two nodes A and B which
want to communicate and there is
no direct link between A and
B. So, it may go via C, D,
E and then B all right.
Now, how do you know
that you have to go through
C, D, E and then you will
actually reach B. So, somebody has
to keep track of the route
how to route the packets over the
entire network. So, that is the job
of the network layer.
Then there is a transport layer that
means how to send packets to the
application. Now, we have been talking
about packets a packet is a
sort of some data which is sort of
has been segregated and put into
a sort of package together.
So, that is a packet,
but the original
application layer need not
have any concept of any packet.
So, somebody has to packetize all this
data and there are may be other
functions in the transport layer.
So, that is the they make packets
out of the data given by the
upper layer. So, that is the
transport layer. Then the session
layer which manages the virtual
connection between in the of the
application layer which manages the
virtual connection and some
properties of this connection we
will talk about it. The presentation
layer that means how do you encode
and decode messages that means two
different machines may have
two different ways of encoding
things. So, there is that is
the job of the presentation layer
as well as the security comes
here and application. So,
whatever the actual job the user is
interested in the human user that
is. So, that comes in the
application layer.
So, the application layer
contains a variety of protocols.
So, it depends on what you are
trying to do. So, the various
users may want to do various things
examples are FTP, Telnet,
SMTP, HTTP, etcetera.
So, these are the names of some
protocols. By the FTP protocol
what you can do is that you
can download files from another
machine. By HTTP you can
look at web pages,
surf, etcetera. There is a
protocol called SMTP
which you use for sending
mails. Now, you may not
be you may not have come
across this protocol directly,
but the point is that whenever
let us say you are sending a mail
from let us say an
unique machine or something you
are using the SMTP protocol
whether or not you know it. So, SMTP
protocol has been built into that.
Similarly, when you
are Telneting that means the
Telnet server and the Telnet client,
etcetera. They will be there in your
machine as a part of the OS maybe.
So, the application there
usually requires reliable and cheap
connection to its pier. That is
what the application layer what it
is concerned about that it must be
connected reliably and cheaply to
its pier. So, examples of pier
we have. So, given some
nodes, given service, etcetera.
Now, application layer
hence this whatever it
has to send to the
presentation layer which handles
as I said the format of the
data. Protocol conversion,
data translation whether it is
ASCII or maybe some other
eBigBig or something to data
compression, data encryption. These
are handled in the presentation
layer. In the session
layer it allows applications and
different computers to share a
connection. Now, what do I mean by
connection? The point is that later
on just as I go to the next layer
you will see that I will
packetize this data. But then
so far as the user is concerned
he wants a continuous connection.
So, this connection is handled
in the session layer. So, it
can provide checkpoints. That
means if there is some disruption
you may come back to it and
sort of get the original
something original state
back and then you can
retransmit if there is some
dialogue control of who can
transmit etcetera. The
transport layer the basic function
of the transport layer is to accept
data from the layer above, split
it into smaller units if necessary.
Now, why we need to split that we
will come to that later on.
So, these are the packets so to
say pass this to the network layer
and ensure that the pieces
all arrive correctly and in the
right order at the other end. For
example, you have chopped them into pieces
now they may become out of order.
So, that is the business of the transport layer.
This should also be done in a
cheap and efficient manner etcetera
the same thing applies.
So, the type or there may be
different types of transport services.
So, there may be multiple protocols
here. One could be error free
point to point channels or it
could be a very cheap kind of channel
or it may broadcasting of messages
to multiple destinations.
So, these are the different types
of transport services which are
possible. The network layer as I
said it decides on what route
to take locally. So, that the
intended message ultimately reaches
the destination. It controls
broadcasting by essentially
segregating the different networks etcetera
it handles technological mismatches.
So, we will get into the details
of this later on. It does congestion
control. It had the handles
billing information etcetera.
And the data link layer
make the physical layer appear
like a channel that is pure transmission
errors. Actually in the physical
layer there may be errors, but the
data link layer handles this error
correction etcetera at the very
lowest level. And finally, at
the lowest level we have the
physical layer where data is
actually transmitted as raw bits
etcetera.
The other layer is TCPIP reference
model where the session and the
presentation layer are not there. So,
we have the application layer,
transport layer, network layer and
maybe something like the data link
or the physical layer. So, the raw
correspondence is something like
this. We have the TCPIP model
where we have just these two and
you have the OSI reference model
with so many. So, more or less
they match the essential functions
match. And there are other kinds
of protocols which are also
used, but the
TCPIP and the OSI these are
the most common.
In the next class we will be
discussing the different
structures of network. So, today
we just had an abstract view of
network. In the next class we
will handle the different structures.
Good day. So,
in this lecture
we will discuss
the network
topology.
Now, what do we
mean by a network
topology? So, let us
just have a quick
recap of
what we had learned last
time. Basically a
computer network
would be a number of nodes
which are connected by some
communication links.
So, there is some kind
of what we usually
call a graph.
So, this graph has certain structure.
So, we talk about the structure.
Now, this structure has an implication
about how we will go
about communicating.
As I said that it is in general
not feasible to have one to
one communication between
each pair of nodes. That is not
possible at all. So, what kind
of structure that means there
is nodes connected in which manner
that is the
subject matter of discussion today.
So,
a network may be
represented as a graph as I said
nodes representing computers
or network devices like switches
routers etcetera
and the links represent communication
links.
Modes of communication may be broadcast
or point to point.
We have discussed this.
Now,
there are various
first let us talk
about the so called LAN topologies.
By
LAN you remember is the
local area network
and local area network topologies
are
three are very common star,
ring and a bus.
So, we will just
look at all of them.
So,
first of all we first
take up this bus topology
and why do we take up a bus topology.
So, this is a very simple
kind of network.
So, this is based on
a shared broadcast
link.
So, this
we want to still want to do
point to point communication. That means
there may be so many nodes a,
b, c, d etcetera
which are
which are connected to the
network and a wants
to communicate to b.
So, c, d are connected
that is all right, but a specifically wants
to communicate to b.
So, each pair of communicating nodes
use the link for a short
time. So, a uses the link
for a short time to send this message to b.
Then after that is over
then maybe c might send
something to d or something like that.
So, other nodes ignore
the communication.
So, since this is shared broadcast
link all the links
all the nodes
get the communication.
So, that is not private in that
sense. So, all the nodes get
that communication, but they usually
will ignore this communication.
Whereas, a b will
sort of copy this for
its own purpose.
Now, there has to be
a distributed protocol to decide
who gets to use the
link. There has to be some protocol.
Otherwise, if a
wants to communicate with b
and b wants to say c wants
to communicate with d,
their communications will go and collide
in the shared broadcast
medium. So, the communication of
both the parties of that
means both the pairs of nodes
they will get garbled.
So, that I mean and sometimes
actually that will happen
that the things will get garbled,
but that is not what we
want to.